<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Om torstein.io on Torstein Norendal: Løsningsarkitekt</title>
    <link>https://torstein.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Om torstein.io on Torstein Norendal: Løsningsarkitekt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 22:59:07 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torstein.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>First Lesson</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/first-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 23:14:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/first-lesson/</guid>
      <description>The first lesson of the EDx CS50 course introduces key concepts related to the problem of search. For example, the solution provided by Google Maps for directions from point A to point B represents a search problem.
Assuming point A is your initial state and point B is your goal state, the available choices at any given state, such as point A, correspond to the actions. The outcome of the search problem depends on the state and the actions as inputs.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The first lesson of the EDx CS50 course introduces key concepts related to the problem of search. For example, the solution provided by Google Maps for directions from point A to point B represents a search problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming point A is your initial state and point B is your goal state, the available choices at any given state, such as point A, correspond to the actions. The outcome of the search problem depends on the state and the actions as inputs. Where you end up depends on what you do, and when and where you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, you will perform a goal test to determine if the current state is equal to the goal state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These concepts are transferable to human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WbzNRTTrX0g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On an AI journey</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/ai-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 21:31:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/ai-journey/</guid>
      <description>ChatGPT shifts my mood. It fills me with optimism and causes me dread. Now everyone on the planet with a mobile device has access to an assistant like Data from Star Trek.
But what may prevent this technology from turning on humanity?
A machine only does what you tell it to do. That observation almost echoes the definition of a machine.
I fear what I don&amp;rsquo;t understand. So every week I will post an update of what I have learned and hopefully understood.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT shifts my mood. It fills me with optimism and causes me dread. Now everyone on the planet with a mobile device has access to an assistant like  Data from Star Trek.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://torstein.io/img/DataTNG.jpg&#34;  alt=&#34;Data from TNG&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But what may prevent this technology from turning on humanity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A machine only does what you tell it to do. That observation almost echoes the definition of a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fear what I don&amp;rsquo;t understand. So every week I will post an update of what I have learned and hopefully understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of any journey is to go through some kind of change. For better or worse: Here I come.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principles for a platform-wide analytics reporting</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/principles-for-a-platform-wide-analytics-reporting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/principles-for-a-platform-wide-analytics-reporting/</guid>
      <description>A platform in this context refers to a group of sites that share important characteristics.
Important questions include:
Who are the users? What do they need? If we have several user groups, we should prioritize and make choices. Which one is more important? And can we help all of them?
We should also take note of their needs today as well as make projections for the future.
Drawing on the previous post I put forward that our data should tell us our state, our direction and provide us with the ability to extract sense from vast quantity of data.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A platform in this context refers to a group of sites that share important characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important questions include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who are the users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do they need?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have several user groups, we should prioritize and make choices. Which one is more important? And can we help all of them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should also take note of their needs today as well as make projections for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://torstein.io/posts/three-ground-rules-for-your-analytics&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I put forward that our data should tell us our state, our direction and provide us with the ability to extract sense from vast quantity of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the vantage point of the biggest user group, the reporting should provide a quick overview of the most important metrics today as well as indicate the trends to let us assess the direction we are going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the platform perspective the reporting should let us quickly navigate from the whole via the subgroup to the relevant site. We should combine numbers and present and aggregated view or views - if we have several subgroups of sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setup should also allow for quickly imlementing more advanced measurements, i.e. &lt;em&gt;events&lt;/em&gt;, that can be pushed to the entire collection of sites, a subgroup or just one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, reporting should be easily pushed to production platform-wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone finds beauty in numbers. To help people understand that these metrics do in fact represent &lt;em&gt;a user&lt;/em&gt; in the aggregate, and that we can infer intentions and behavior from these numbers, several avenues are worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we should provide context for the data. A short text describing the what the numbers refer to may suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we should present the information in bite-sized pieces where the most important metrics take precedence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we should let interested users dig through their data by drilling down into their reports. And in the case the reports available cannot reveal what the user desires from them, we should let people make simple feature requests – in that context.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three ground rules for your analytics setup</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/three-ground-rules-for-your-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/three-ground-rules-for-your-analytics/</guid>
      <description>There are three key elements to a strong analytics setup. Whatever your system, workflow or software you need this needs to be in place. The essence is simple:
1. State Your data will not tell you what you need to know. You will have to instruct it. When you look out the window, you can tell what the weather is like. Your data should at first glance indicate how you are doing.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;There are three key elements to a strong analytics setup. Whatever your system, workflow or software you need this needs to be in place. The essence is simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-state&#34;&gt;1. State&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your data will not tell you what you need to know. You will have to instruct it. When you look out the window, you can tell what the weather is like. Your data should at first glance indicate how you are doing. Are your performing well right now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have easy access to your most important metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-direction&#34;&gt;2. Direction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you tell if you&amp;rsquo;re going in the right direction? How far do you have left?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map out the key indicators over time. Let them tell you the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-the-ability-ask-your-data-the-right-questions&#34;&gt;3. The ability ask your data the right questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not every question you get from product development or management can easily be answered. In most cases your rows and columns tell you nothing. But perhaps the answer is swimming somewhere in your ocean of data. But how do you find it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to ask your data the questions. It does not have be anything fancy. You don’t need a machine learning algorithm. You don’t need an AI. What you do need is a way to extract meaning from your data. Pulling data and pasting them into Sheets pivot table may be fine. As long as you know how to communicate with your data to find the answer you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State, direction and the ability ask your data the right questions, will give you the backbone you need - no matter the tool, the organization or the matter at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planning is overrated – looking ahead is not</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/planning-is-overrated-looking-ahead-is-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/planning-is-overrated-looking-ahead-is-not/</guid>
      <description>Look ahead. There&amp;rsquo;s always hope. There are always opportunities.
Don&amp;rsquo;t get bogged down by the details. But set the course.
You cannot know all the things that may go wrong. And we often underestimate learning and creativity along the way.
So here&amp;rsquo;s to full steam ahead.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Look ahead. There&amp;rsquo;s always hope. There are always opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get bogged down by the details. But set the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cannot know all the things that may go wrong. And we often underestimate learning and creativity along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s to full steam ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setbacks and comebacks: On fortitude</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/fortitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/fortitude/</guid>
      <description>Resilience. Grit. Toughness.
Setbacks may bring major concerns. What doesn&amp;rsquo;t kill you, does not make you stronger. They set you back.
Some will say you&amp;rsquo;ll grow scar tissue, you&amp;rsquo;ll become thick-skinned, you&amp;rsquo;ll develop fortitude. But that&amp;rsquo;s not the case. Instead, you will recognize patterns.
The next time you&amp;rsquo;ll see the wrecking ball coming - and calculate its velocity. It will crush the building, but you will get out of the way.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Resilience. Grit. Toughness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setbacks may bring major concerns. What doesn&amp;rsquo;t kill you, does  &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; make you stronger. They set you back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some will say you&amp;rsquo;ll grow scar tissue, you&amp;rsquo;ll become thick-skinned, you&amp;rsquo;ll develop fortitude. But that&amp;rsquo;s not the case.
Instead, you will recognize patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you&amp;rsquo;ll see the wrecking ball coming - and calculate its velocity. It will crush the building, but you will get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working slow and fast: How to benefit from both modes of thinking</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/working-slow-fast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/working-slow-fast/</guid>
      <description>Whenever I want go deep, I am distracted by things “I need to do”. And that’s true: If I do not adress them, my work will suffer.
And whenever do I block out everything that is not related to the deeper task at hand, I am constantly on the lookout for fast decisions that require little understanding, but help me feel productive. In effect, that work dampens real progress.
But when I do succeed at working slow and coming up with a feasible solution to a deeper problem, I manage to reach decisions on other questions much faster.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Whenever I want go deep, I am distracted by things “I need to do”. And that’s true: If I do not adress them, my work will suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And whenever do I block out everything that is not related to the deeper task at hand, I am constantly on the lookout for fast decisions that require little understanding, but help me feel productive. In effect, that work dampens real progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I do succeed at working slow and coming up with a feasible solution to a deeper problem, I manage to reach decisions on other questions much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there an interplay between working fast and slow? Can the two processes interact in a meaningful way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could refer to these distinct processes as ‘closed’ and ‘open’ – akin to the double diamond where you seek to ask and frame questions before you try to answer them in a separate phase. You will need both modes to arrive at a good solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes, the surface problems are related to the deeper set of problems – they appear at the surface because of deeper issues. So in a sense they provide feedback that push me toward working on the underlying problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a silver lining to switching between slow and fast? I believe there is one. By solving the deeper problems, I tackle the surface problems much easier. And surface problems help inform the deeper problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it requires discipline. Because we can’t do both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You are what you do - or how our tools define us</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/you-are-what-you-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/you-are-what-you-do/</guid>
      <description>Someone said: First we shape our tools, then they shape us.
Excel is an excellent tool for long-term planning in a low-res perspective in a rigorous | unflexible manner.
Word is good for producing longstanding documents that dictate the solutions long after the problems were forgotten.
Powerpoint is a great helper when you want to persuade or put your foot in the door. And many gatekeepers require a deck to say yes.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Someone said: First we shape our tools, then they shape us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excel is an excellent tool for long-term planning in a low-res perspective in a rigorous | unflexible manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word is good for producing longstanding documents that dictate the solutions long after the problems were forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powerpoint is a great helper when you want to persuade or put your foot in the door. And many gatekeepers require a deck to say yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these are bad tools. Nor do they represent any malign influence in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is  some flexibility for you to choose right the tool when addressing a problem. But as a rule, the problem at hand determines what tool is right for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: Seek out the problems that require the tools you want to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology is what we don’t understand</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/technology-is-what-we-dont-understand/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/technology-is-what-we-dont-understand/</guid>
      <description>We all want fixes. We want simple solutions. We want someone to take away our worries.
But we do not want or need to understand how.
Because once we understand how, the magic disappears. The emperor has no clothes. It was a trick.
And the belief in magic keeps us going. It motivates us to look for the next technological fix. We all want to believe.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We all want fixes. We want simple solutions. We want someone to take away our worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we do not want or need to understand how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because once we understand how, the magic disappears. The emperor has no clothes. It was a trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the belief in magic keeps us going. It motivates us to look for the next technological fix. We all want to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fragmenting the user: How complexity can undermine your product</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/fragmenting-the-user/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/fragmenting-the-user/</guid>
      <description>The user doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist. No one conforms to this abstraction. Yet, it is useful.
Many discussions on design revolve around simplicity: How can we make this feature easier to understand, how can we make this product more intuitive, how can we simplify this design?
Adding multiple user types increases the number of factors exponentially. Complexity and competing priorities appear as a result.
Successful products are strategically mono-dimensional. The interesting question is not: How many personas do we need?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The user doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist. No one conforms to this abstraction. Yet, it is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many discussions on design revolve around simplicity: How can we make this feature easier to understand, how can we make this product more intuitive, how can we simplify this design?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding multiple user types increases the number of factors exponentially. Complexity and competing priorities appear as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful products are strategically mono-dimensional. The interesting question is not: &lt;em&gt;How many personas do we need?&lt;/em&gt; Rather, the question you want to answer is: &lt;strong&gt;Who is my user?&lt;/strong&gt; Allowing for some degrees of freedom with respect to demographics, computer fluency, and domain knowledge, are well within the bounds of the user as a device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to make everyone happy, is a losing proposition. Tearing the user down, will make everyone worse off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The user&lt;/strong&gt; is a powerful construct that will help you move toward your product vision and help keep the team aligned. It will simplify most choices – for you and your users.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sticky elements on mobile that work</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/sticky-elements-on-mobile-that-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/sticky-elements-on-mobile-that-work/</guid>
      <description>In our investigation of this we found no other way to present table of contents to help people navigate and read long medical treatment texts. We decided to go for a sticky TOC on mobile and smaller screens.
Having gone back and forth for some time on sticky elements on really long pages, here&amp;rsquo;s what we&amp;rsquo;ve learned:
sticky elements are annoying as a rule they should not be used but exceptions do exist So when do sticky elements on mobile actually help the user?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In our investigation of this we found no other way to present &lt;em&gt;table of contents&lt;/em&gt; to help people navigate and read long medical treatment texts. We decided to go for a sticky TOC on mobile and smaller screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having gone back and forth for some time on sticky elements on &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; long pages, here&amp;rsquo;s what we&amp;rsquo;ve learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sticky elements are annoying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a rule they should not be used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but exceptions do exist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when do sticky elements on mobile actually help the user?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they should not take up a lot of real estate on the screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they should be smooth and feel natural&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they should provide an entry point to something that is otherwise out of reach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;they should be fast and not hinder performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case we think that providing a sticky table of contents prevent lostness. It helps the user to anchor the paragraph or section in focus. And it helps the transition from one area of the page to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preferably we avoid using the margins of the page and seek to use the bottom. That way we hope to provide a clear navigation pattern without disrupting the reading experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment we&amp;rsquo;re user testing these options to find the optimal solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gerry McGovern on navigation</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/gerry-mcgovern-on-navigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 05:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/gerry-mcgovern-on-navigation/</guid>
      <description>In Gerry McGovern&amp;rsquo;s book on top tasks he describes seven principles of effective digital navigation:
Momentum
Keep people moving forward
Unity
Make navigation as unified as possible.
Twins
Design for the journey customers are on.
Minimalism
Have navigation take up as little space as is practical.
Clarity
Navigation must immediately communicate what it is – and what it is not.
Fidelity
A link is a promise – navigation should keep its promises.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In Gerry McGovern&amp;rsquo;s book on top tasks he describes seven principles of effective digital navigation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Keep people moving forward&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Make navigation as unified as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Design for the journey customers are on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Have navigation take up as little space as is practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Navigation must immediately communicate what it is – and what it is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fidelity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
A link is a promise – navigation should keep its promises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Magnetism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Maximize clean magnetism, minimize dirty magnetism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Top-Tasks-How-Gerry-McGovern-ebook/dp/B07JJKZNZ6&#34;&gt;Top Tasks: A How-to Guide&lt;/a&gt; (No affiliation)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Om navigasjon og innholdsstruktur</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/navigasjon-og-innholdsstruktur/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 06:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/navigasjon-og-innholdsstruktur/</guid>
      <description>Det er gunstig å skille mellom innholdsstrukturen og navigasjonssystemet.
Innholdsstrukturen viser til den hierarkiske organiseringen, mens navigasjonssystemet primært hjelper brukeren med å navigere til det viktigste innholdet. Dette skjer i meny, footer og eventuelt med brødsmulesti.
Navigasjonssystemet Meny Denne skal gjenspeile de viktigste brukeroppgavene, ikke være en nøyaktig refleksjon av den underliggende strukturen.
Menyen får en blanding av disse elementene: De viktigste kjernesidene der toppoppgavene blir løst De viktigste seksjonene og underseksjonene som har innganger til toppoppgavene Temasidene som sørger for innholdsbasert navigasjon til innholdet Brukereoppgavene blir utgangspunktet for formuleringene av elementene i menyen.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Det er gunstig å skille mellom innholdsstrukturen og navigasjonssystemet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innholdsstrukturen viser til den hierarkiske organiseringen, mens navigasjonssystemet primært hjelper brukeren med å navigere til det viktigste innholdet. Dette skjer i meny, footer og eventuelt med brødsmulesti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;navigasjonssystemet&#34;&gt;Navigasjonssystemet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;meny&#34;&gt;Meny&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denne skal gjenspeile de viktigste brukeroppgavene, ikke være en nøyaktig refleksjon av den underliggende strukturen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Menyen får en blanding av disse elementene: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;De viktigste kjernesidene der toppoppgavene blir løst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;De viktigste seksjonene og underseksjonene som har innganger til toppoppgavene&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temasidene som sørger for innholdsbasert navigasjon til innholdet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brukereoppgavene blir utgangspunktet for formuleringene av elementene i menyen. Bruk de sterkeste triggerordene og typografisk hierarki for å få fram det prioriterte innholdet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muligens kan du gi elementene få visuell tyngde etter relevans for brukeren og få formen stor, medium, liten. Denne menyen kan du skissere mer eller mindre detaljert og teste i &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.optimalworkshop.com/chalkmark&#34;&gt;Chalkmark&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sidekart&#34;&gt;Sidekart?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Med et dynamisk sidekart som innholdssystemet oppdaterer får brukeren (i den grad det er et behov) en full oversikt over alt innhold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dette kartet skal sørge for at de brukerne som trenger en presis mental modell av nettstedet, kan få det.  Dette har også vært en tradisjonell SEO-teknikk som fortsatt skal ha noe relevans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sidekartet får også en inngang i menyen. Dette er old fashion, men parallelt med denne kan du enklere få en tight og brukerorientert meny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footer&#34;&gt;Footer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Konvesjonelt spiller footeren en begrenset med lite innhold og lister primært ut følgende:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kontaktinformasjon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sosiale medier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inngang til menyen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;brødsmulesti&#34;&gt;Brødsmulesti&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dette er effektivt hos informasjonstunge nettsteder og kan være en kandidat her. Den hjelper folk å navigere mellom sidenivåer og bidrar til brukerens mentale modell. På mindre skjermer kan du vise kun nivået over. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;innholdsstrukturen&#34;&gt;Innholdsstrukturen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innholdet blir som regel strukturert hierarkisk i et tre. I tillegg har du gjerne temasider som binder innhold sammen, men de kan eksistere på det øverste nivået og ha minst mulig innhold direkte under seg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dagens innholdsstruktur danner utgangspunktet for arbeidet med å organisere det på nytt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Til dette arbeidet er det nytte i få god hjelp av oppdragsgiveren. Det setter spørsmålet på agendaen og sparer deg for en del jobb. Ellers er det fullt mulig å få bygd en god oversikt ved hjelp av en crawl eller Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;treejack-testing&#34;&gt;Treejack-testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Har du godt definerte brukeroppgaver fra oppgaveundersøkelser som Customer Carewords eller Task Analytics er det en god kilde til gode Treejack-oppgaver. Kjør gjerne flere tester slik at du får raffinert deg fram til en god struktur. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epost-lista hjelper deg med å få tak i nok folk. Sender du ut til for eksempel en tredel den første gangen, kan du teste iterasjoner – og på den måten nå målet om 80%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lykke til.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the separation of user research and design</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/user-research-and-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 15:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/user-research-and-design/</guid>
      <description>Twice I have had a falling out regarding the utility of user research. On those two occasions I have failed to build an understanding of my perspective. I encountered what I would like to call the value-free user research perspective.
This lofty ideal is alluring: We as design researchers can provide truth to the designers given enough time and money. But no-one can do this – and if some godlike person could give us a complete understanding of the user, no-one would need it because that knowledge is only valuable to the extent that it may be related to the product.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Twice I have had a falling out regarding the utility of user research. On those two occasions I have failed to build an understanding of my perspective. I encountered what I would like to call the value-free user research perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lofty ideal is alluring: We as design researchers can provide truth to the designers given enough time and money. But no-one can do this – and if some godlike person could give us a complete understanding of the user,  no-one would need it because that knowledge is only valuable to the extent that it may be related to the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;because&#34;&gt;Because:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing as open inquiry - every investigation into the user experience is motivated by beliefs and ideas, no matter how shaky their grounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is better to be open about one’s own presuppositions and ideas than trying to maintain the blank facade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want actionable insight that is easily shared within the team. There are specific questions that need answers. To increase the signal-to-noise ratio highlight your findings, forget the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviews can give an initial understanding, interaction sketches may provide some feedback. But to gain a high-level understanding of the user and the design, you will need an interaction with a high-fidelity prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clickable sketches seem like the easy way out, but they are a dead end street in the design process. Instead of building the product and get feedback along the way, you iterate on sketches by drawing more and more connections between them – creating design spaghetti. It may feel good, but you’ll only postpone important decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do not need to test everything. Because user experience conventions work. Test as specifically as possible where you need help to make choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So start guessing and get the feedback you need.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Er du et verktøy eller et produkt?</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/verktoy-eller-produkt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 15:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/verktoy-eller-produkt/</guid>
      <description>Boka E-myth Revisited sier at det øyeblikket der du går fra å jobbe i butikken til å jobbe med butikken din, er tidspunktet der du tar styringen.
Men gjelder ikke det også meg og deg? Visst skal vi pumpe ut arbeid og levere – men bør vi ikke sørge for at outputen vår i morgen er mer verdt enn i dag?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Boka &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Myth-Revisited-Small-Businesses-About-ebook/dp/B000RO9VJK/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=emyth+revisited&amp;amp;qid=1570993795&amp;amp;sr=8-1&#34;&gt;E-myth Revisited&lt;/a&gt; sier at det øyeblikket der du går fra å jobbe i butikken til å jobbe &lt;em&gt;med&lt;/em&gt; butikken din, er tidspunktet der du tar styringen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men gjelder ikke det også meg og deg? Visst skal vi pumpe ut arbeid og levere – men bør vi ikke sørge for at outputen vår i morgen er mer verdt enn i dag?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Innovasjon vs. gjennomførbarhet i prosjekter</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/posts/innovasjon-vs-gjennomforbarhet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 15:08:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/posts/innovasjon-vs-gjennomforbarhet/</guid>
      <description>Som eksperter for Forskningsrådet skal vi gi prosjekter karakter etter hvor innovative de er og hvor gjennomførbare de er. Jeg merket etter hvert at dette ble en liten øvelse i kompromiss:
Er prosjektet innovativt, blir det sannsynligvis vanskelig å gjennomføre det til punkt og prikke i henhold til plan. Er derimot prosjektet gjennomførbart, er det kanskje ikke så innovativt.
De som skåret midddels på begge faktorene oppfattet jeg som pregløse og uinteressante.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Som eksperter for Forskningsrådet skal vi gi prosjekter karakter etter hvor innovative de er og hvor gjennomførbare de er. Jeg merket etter hvert at dette ble en liten øvelse i kompromiss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Er prosjektet innovativt, blir det sannsynligvis vanskelig å gjennomføre det til punkt og prikke i henhold til plan. Er derimot prosjektet gjennomførbart, er det kanskje ikke så innovativt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De som skåret midddels på begge faktorene oppfattet jeg som pregløse og uinteressante.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hverken svært gjennomføre eller middels innovative prosjekter har tiltrekningskraft. Det må være noe energisk i et prosjekt skal det fenge dem som skal skape resultatene. Det må være snakk om en reell innovasjon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Thiel snakker om å gå fra null til en: å lage noe som ikke finnes fra - eller å lage 10x forbedring av noe eksisterende.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Er det målet, feiler ofte innovasjon. Men den som ikke våger, vinner heller ikke.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Om</title>
      <link>https://torstein.io/om/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torstein.io/om/</guid>
      <description>Som løsningsarkitekt konkretiserer jeg spørsmål og foreslår en retning på løsningen. Enten i form av skisser, modeller eller tekst.
Denne detaljerer teamet og jeg. Dit skal vi.
Jeg tror på eierskap og autonomi. Ingenting binder team sterkere sammen enn en felles oppgave. Ved å løse vanskelige problemer sammen, går vi fra jeg til vi. Da får også fjernbingo på hjemmekontoret en verdi.
Når jeg har det strategiske perspektivet, vekter de faglige bidragene og styrer mot produktvisjonen bidrar jeg mest.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Som løsningsarkitekt konkretiserer jeg spørsmål og foreslår en retning på løsningen. Enten i form av skisser, modeller eller tekst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denne detaljerer teamet og jeg. Dit skal vi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeg tror på eierskap og autonomi. Ingenting binder team sterkere sammen enn en felles oppgave. Ved å løse vanskelige problemer sammen, går vi fra jeg til vi. Da får også fjernbingo på hjemmekontoret en verdi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Når jeg har det strategiske perspektivet, vekter de faglige bidragene og styrer mot produktvisjonen bidrar jeg mest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;kontakt&#34;&gt;Kontakt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;911 28 335&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:torstein.norendal@gmail.com&#34;&gt;torstein.norendal@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;prosjekter&#34;&gt;Prosjekter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Migrering, redesign og nykonstruksjon av Felles nettløsning for spesialisthelsetjenesten (2022 - 2023)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Teamleder, Optimizely DXP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Felles nettløsning for spesialisthelsetjenesten (2020 - 2023 )&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Produktansvarlig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dyrehelsenett (2022)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Løsningsarkitektur for en norsk kunnskapsplattform for dyrehelse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Felles nettløsning for spesialisthelsetjenesten (2019 - 2020)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Funksjonelt ansvarlig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lausanne 2020: OL for ungdom (2019)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lærdal Medical (2018 - 2019)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av prosjektapp&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direktoratet for e-helse (2019)&lt;/strong&gt;: Nye ehelse.no&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;American Express (2019)&lt;/strong&gt;: Brukertest med live overføring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sykepleien (2018)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av magasinet&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Veterinærinstituttet (2015 - 2018)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av vetinst.no, digitalisering av tjenester&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;helsenorge.no (2017)&lt;/strong&gt;: Brukerinnsikt og strategisk rådgivning&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Universitetet i Oslo (2017)&lt;/strong&gt;: Tjenestedesignworkshop, onboarding av nye studenter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dagens Næringsliv (2017)&lt;/strong&gt;: Tjenestedesignworkshop, segmentert kundereise med strategi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norway bussekspress (2017)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av billettkjøp&lt;br&gt;
Interaksjonsdesigner og innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norsk Filminstitutt (2016)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av visuell identitet og nfi.no&lt;br&gt;
Innholdsrådgiver og Interaksjonsdesigner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ungdoms-OL Lillehammer 2016 (2015)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sonans (2015 - 2016 )&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign av sonans.no&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oslo kommune (2016)&lt;/strong&gt;: Analyse og UX-rådgivning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statens vegvesen (2015)&lt;/strong&gt;: Innholdsstrategi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norwegian (2014 - 2015)&lt;/strong&gt;: Redesign norwegian.com&lt;br&gt;
Engelsk innhold og stil og tone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;arbeid&#34;&gt;Arbeid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Athena (2019 - )&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Løsningsarkitekt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netlife (2015 - 2019)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Innholdsrådgiver, interaksjonsdesigner og prosjektleder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovasjon Norge (2012- 2014)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Selvstendig innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sigarett Design (2011)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Innholdsrådgiver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innholdsrådgiver og oversetter (2009 - 2010)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tekniske tekster og journalistikk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webredaktør og tekstforfatter (2002)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
expert.no, panasonic.no og bestbuy.no&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;utdanning&#34;&gt;Utdanning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Master i statsvitenskap, UiO (2006 - 2008)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.duo.uio.no/handle/10852/14883&#34;&gt;Oppgave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin (2008)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tysk og amerikansk politikk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bachelor i komparativ politikk, UiB (2003 - 2006)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aix-Marseille Université (2004)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fransk og økonomi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tysk for næringslivet, NHH (2003)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;kurs&#34;&gt;Kurs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional Scrum Product Owner 1 (2020)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Scrum.org&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prince2 (2018)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Foundation + Practitioner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snomed CT Foundation (2020)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Analytics IQ (2016)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ferdigheter&#34;&gt;Ferdigheter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tilegne seg mye informasjon på kort tid og trekke ut hovedpunkter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;planlegge, konseptualisere og detaljere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;koordinere og kommunisere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gjennomføre og levere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
